<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Academic</title>
    <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 17:20:53 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://vdkabanova.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create a report</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 17:20:53 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small recipe that will be useful when creating dynamic reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite often there is a situation when the size and content of the reporting form will depend on the composition of the data transmitted to the input. We are talking about a story-telling report, and not about a simple table output. In this case, depending on the content of the input data, individual items, graphs, tables, text may appear or disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will a classic Excel-Word analyst do? For each new request, make a custom report and save it to a separate file. But you can look a little under the hood and make the computer do everything on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R Markdown lets you do all this in an elegant way. Some technical details below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main idea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have data, the content of which may change. For example, it is necessary to build a report on cars delivering goods (abstract example). The number and numbers of cars leaving for the flight are different every day, but the summary for each car is the same in its structure. Let&amp;rsquo;s move on from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R Markdown is done in multiple passes. At the same time, .md is first formed from Rmd, and then the output representation is formed from it, the most popular is the html format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, there are 2 options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can insert the necessary blocks (assembled or templated) into the compiled .Rmd at the stage of compiling the report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can insert the necessary markdown inserts into the intermediate .md at the stage of compiling the report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is just an example of code that anyone can run on their machine. It covers implementations of both examples and is minimal to get the point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamically insert hyperlinks received from an external source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamically generate document sections based on data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lightweight markup languages</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 17:20:53 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markup language with simple unobtrusive syntax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Lightweight Markup Language (LML), also called Plain Markup Language or Humane Markup Language, is a markup language with a simple, unobtrusive syntax. It is designed to be easy to write using any generic and easy to read in raw form. Lightweight markup languages ​​are used in applications where the raw document may need to be read as well as the final rendered output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a person downloading a software library may prefer to read the documentation in a text editor rather than in a web browser. Another application for such languages ​​is to provide data entry in web publications, such as weblogs and wikis, where the input interface is a simple text field. The server software then converts the input into a common document markup language such as HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Story&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightweight markup languages ​​were originally used on text displays that could not display italic or bold characters, so informal methods had to be developed to communicate this information. This formatting choice has naturally been applied to plain text emails. Console browsers may also use similar rendering conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1986, the international standard SGML provided a means to define and parse lightweight markup languages ​​using grammars and tag implication. 1998 W3C XML is an SGML profile that does not have these features. However, the SGML Document Type Definition (DTD) for any of the languages ​​listed below is not known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Types&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightweight markup languages ​​can be categorized by their tag types. Similar to HTML (bold), some languages ​​use named elements that have a common format for start and end tags (e.g. BBCode[b] bold [ / b] ), while proper simplified markup languages ​​are limited to ASCII-only punctuation and others non-letter characters for tags, but some also mix both styles (eg Textile bq. ) or allow inline HTML (eg Markdown ), perhaps extended with custom elements (eg MediaWiki source ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most languages ​​distinguish between markup for lines or blocks and shorter sections of text, but some only support inline markup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some markup languages ​​are designed for a specific purpose, such as documenting computer code (e.g. POD, RD) or converting to a specific output format (usually HTML) and nothing else, others more generally in an application. This includes whether they are oriented towards text representation or data serialization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentation-oriented languages ​​include AsciiDoc, atx, BBCode, Creole, Crossmark, Epytext, Haml, JsonML, MakeDoc, Markdown, Org-mode, POD, reST, RD, Setext, SiSU, SPIP, Xupl, Texy! , Textile , txt2tags , UDO and Wikitext .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data serialization-oriented languages ​​include Curl (homoicon, but also reads JSON; each object is serialized), JSON, and YAML.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific programming languages</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post8/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 17:20:53 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming in science: relevance and relevance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is often mentioned in an applied context. It seems that only mobile applications, Internet systems and special effects for cinema are created with its help. But initially programming was intended to solve scientific problems. In addition, programming itself is a science, which will be useful to learn about for those who decide to link their careers with computer development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific programming is a highly oriented programming style for scientific computing. It is distinguished from other types of programming by the extreme correctness and stability of the final product, the strict separation of scientific and interface parts, the individuality of algorithms, and the predominance of efficiency over universality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific programming is at the heart of any modern global research. All advanced technologies - from quantum computers to space programs - would not be possible without scientific programmers who can provide scientists with a reliable and accurate tool for making discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of branches of science directly depend on the level of development of scientific programming. So, unmanned vehicles, “smart” management systems for urban and agricultural management, stock exchanges are waiting for their implementation; waiting for robotics, genetic engineering, artificial intelligence that surpasses human capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specialization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists use various programming languages, the choice of which depends on the type of problem and the preferences of the author. Historically, the first high-level programming language is Fortran; many debugged libraries of mathematical statistics and libraries for solving differential equations are written on it, which is relevant for economics and biology, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python has a simpler syntax, which is also suitable for programming mathematical calculations. The Python language is used for data processing in mathematics, physics, economics, biology, chemistry and can work with some other &amp;ldquo;scientific&amp;rdquo; languages: Fortran, C++, C#.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In turn, C# allows you to program on the .NET platform, adapt the program to the common language runtime (CLR), and accelerate development within the framework of operational scientific sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The future of the programmer-scientist profession&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming drives science, which drives technological progress. Inventions that were considered revolutionary yesterday serve everyday needs in the 21st century: a microwave oven, a mobile phone, an 8-bit home computer. It depends on the programmer-scientist what peaks science will reach today and which of them will enter every house tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hands of a programmer-scientist are the tools not only to develop the industry, but also to improve the overall quality of life. Such a specialist increases the prognostic function of humanity, helping to predict and prevent climate, financial, and humanitarian disasters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where can I learn to code?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can learn programming anytime, anywhere. Specialized literature, face-to-face training, Internet sites - all these resources are able to provide a novice programmer with a knowledge base sufficient for independent creativity and advanced training, including in line with scientific development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GeekBrains portal offers users free courses for beginners in programming. Additionally, training is provided for 15 professions that are most in demand on the labor market: Python programmer, C # developer, Senior Web Developer and others. Upon completion of each course, graduates are guaranteed an internship from GeekBrains&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Versioning. Git</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 17:20:53 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is a &amp;ldquo;version control system&amp;rdquo; and why is it important?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Version Control System (VCS) is software that makes it easier to work with changing information. The version control system allows you to store multiple versions of the same document, revert to earlier versions if necessary, determine who made a change and when, and much more. Such systems are most widely used in software development to store the source codes of the program being developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GIT is a distributed version control system created by Linus Torvalds to manage the development of the Linux kernel and is currently very widespread among software developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GIT uses a distributed model instead of the traditional client-server model. Thus, GIT repositories do not need a centralized repository: the entire history of document changes is stored on each computer, in local storage, and, if necessary, individual fragments of the local storage history are synchronized with the same storage on another computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, GIT has become the standard version control system for so many developers, and GitHub source code hosting is the largest such service. Examples of projects using Git are the Linux kernel, Android, Ruby on Rails, Drupal, Wine, Chromium, Compiz Fusion, jQuery, PHP, MediaWiki, and some Linux distributions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why should a beginner learn Git?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git is used in most companies where at least two developers work on a project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new person comes to the company and clones the project repository on the PC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gets an issue, creates a new branch, and writes the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When everything is ready - sends a request to add code to the master branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other developers look at the code, leave comments and point out bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A beginner refines the code, updates the master branch and moves on to the next task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a general outline of how teamwork works in a project. It does not take into account the rules for using Git, which each team writes for itself. For example, each team has its own code review order and its own criteria for its readiness to be added to the master branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing Git and knowing how to use Git in a team are two different skills that can be compared to knowing how to drive a car and knowing the rules of the road. If you know how to drive a car, it is easier for you to concentrate and quickly learn the rules. With Git, the situation is similar: if you know how to manage the version control system, then you can immediately join the project, not be distracted by secondary things and focus on the quality of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog 05/05</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 16:51:07 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I completed two labs (#3, #4) on operating systems, and did the first part of an individual project. I went to my parents in my hometown.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog 12/05</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 16:51:07 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I completed two labs (#5, #6) on operating systems, and did the second part of an individual project. I got a job, filmed a hockey match mirea-rudn&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog 19/05</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 16:51:07 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I completed two labs (#7, #8) on operating systems, got a job&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog 27/05</title>
      <link>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post7/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 16:51:07 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vdkabanova.github.io/post/post7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I completed two labs (# 9, # 10) on operating systems, went to the Bolshoi and Maly Theater&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
